A Guide to the John A. Hartford Foundation records, Foundation Publications and History, Series 7 FA1138
Rockefeller Archive Center
John A. Hartford Foundation records, Foundation Publications and History, Series 7
1958-2015
Rockefeller Archive Center
John A. Hartford Foundation
FA1138
4.9 Cubic Feet 12 document boxes; 1 flat box
Scope and Contents Note
This series contains an amalgam of institutional records dating from 1958 to 2015, plus a single declined grant from 1984. There are JAHF annual reports from 1958 to 2015, as well as a run of JAHF Bulletins from 1966 to 1978. Additionally, Boxes 526 to 532 contain records on the planning, writing, and distribution of the institutional history of the foundation. This was referred to as the History Project and went through several iterations before publication of "The Greatest Good" in 1984.
Other records in this series include strategic plan presentations to the foundation's board by president Corinne Rieder, lease details and blueprints of the former JAHF offices in the Chrysler Building in Manhattan, and accounting records from the estate of John A. Hartford for the Cemetery Trust that maintained a family plot in Hillside Cemetery in Middletown, New York.
Biographical/Historical Note
The John A. Hartford Foundation (JAHF) was established in 1929 by brothers John and George Hartford, sons of the founder of the Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company (A&P). The foundation is a private, nonpartisan philanthropy dedicated to improving the care of older adults. For its first several decades, the foundation broadly supported clinical medical research. By 1982, it began to focus solely on geriatric healthcare. In 2015, JAHF paid out $20.2 million on a total of 80 active grants and committed $25.3 million to 24 new grants projects, all focused on the care of older adults.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The John A. Hartford Foundation records were donated to RAC by JAHF in 2014. Record transfers to RAC began in 2014 and continue as needed.
Arrangement Note
Arranged as received
Conditions Governing Access Note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Other Finding Aids Note
For Series 1 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA771/collection
For Series 2 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1137/collection
For Series 3 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1218/collection
For Series 4 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1296/collection
For Series 5 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1297/collection
For Series 6 of the John A. Hartford Foundation records, see http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1326/collection
- Foundation Publications and History, 7
  - Annual Reports, 1958-1994 (Box 524, Folder 3904-3910)
  - Annual Reports, 1994-2006 (Box 525, Folder 3911-3915)
  - Annual Reports, 2007-2015 (Box 526, Folder 3916-3918)
  - John A. Hartford Foundation Bulletin, Numbers 1-16, 1966-1978 (Box 526, Folder 3919)
  - The Greatest Good: History of the John A. Hartford Foundation, 1984 (Box 526, Folder 3920)
  - History Project: Project Planning, 1979-1980 (Box 527, Folder 3921)
  - History Project: Update, 1980 (Box 527, Folder 3922)
  - History Project: Howard Fields Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 527, Folder 3923)
  - History Project: Howard Fields Contract, 1980 (Box 527, Folder 3924)
  - History Project: Joan Spivak Files on Publishers, 1980-1981 (Box 527, Folder 3925)
  - History Project: Author Proposals, 1979-1980 (Box 527, Folder 3926-3927)
  - History Project: Howard Fields Progress, 1980-1981 (Box 528, Folder 3928)
  - History Project: Howard Fields Drafts, 1980-1981 (Box 528, Folder 3929)
  - History Project: Howard Fields Correspondence, 1981 (Box 528, Folder 3930)
  - History Project: Introduction to Chapter 2, 1981 (Box 528, Folder 3931)
  - History Project: Chapters 3 to 5, 1981 (Box 528, Folder 3932)
  - History Project: Chapters 6 to 8, 1981 (Box 528, Folder 3933)
  - History Project: Chapters 9 to 11, 1981 (Box 529, Folder 3934)
  - History Project: Chapter 12 to Appendix, 1981 (Box 529, Folder 3935)
  - History Project: Judith Jacobson Editorial Services, 1981-1983 (Box 529, Folder 3936)
  - History Project: Permissions, 1983-1984 (Box 529, Folder 3937)
  - History Project: Mailing Lists, 1983-1984 (Box 529, Folder 3938)
  - History Project: Thank-yous, 1984 (Box 529, Folder 3939)
  - History Project: Committee on the History Project, 1979-1980 (Box 529, Folder 3940)
  - History Project: Judith Jacobson, 1981-1982 (Box 529, Folder 3941)
  - History Project: Summaries and Costs, 1980-1982 (Box 529, Folder 3942)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with Gilbert Coburn, 1979 August 22 (Box 530, Folder 3943)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with F. L. Handy, 1979 July 31 (Box 530, Folder 3944)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with Byron Jay, 1979 August 1 (Box 530, Folder 3945)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with William Kolff, 1979 September 14 (Box 530, Folder 3946)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with Robert Mulreany, 1979 July 25 (Box 530, Folder 3947)
  - History Project: Transcript of Interview with E. Pierre Roy, 1979 August 9 (Box 530, Folder 3948)
  - History Project: Walter Unger Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 530, Folder 3949)
  - History Project: Joseph Falkson Correspondence, 1979 (Box 530, Folder 3950)
  - History Project: Stephen Strickland Correspondence, 1979 (Box 530, Folder 3951)
  - History Project: Walter Unger Phase I, 1979 (Box 530, Folder 3952-3953)
  - History Project: Phase II, 1979-1980 (Box 530, Folder 3954)
  - History Project: Planning, 1979-1982 (Box 531, Folder 3955)
  - History Project: Author, 1980-1983 (Box 531, Folder 3956)
  - History Project: Judith Jacobson, 1983 (Box 531, Folder 3957)
  - History Project: Judith Jacobson Agreement, 1983 (Box 531, Folder 3958)
  - History Project: Memos, 1979-1981 (Box 531, Folder 3959)
  - History Project: John A. Hartford Foundation History Summaries, 1980 (Box 531, Folder 3960)
  - History Project: Judith Jacobson and Howard Fields, 1982-1983 (Box 531, Folder 3961)
  - History Project: Background Information for Introduction, 1979 (Box 531, Folder 3962)
  - History Project: Background Information for Chapter I, 1979 (Box 531, Folder 3963)
  - History Project: Background Information for Chapter XII, 1979 (Box 531, Folder 3964)
  - History Project: Background Information for Chapter XVII, 1979 (Box 531, Folder 3965)
  - History Project: Background Information for Epilogue, 1979 (Box 531, Folder 3966)
  - History Project: Photo Planning for Book, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3967)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter III Kidney Transplants, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3968)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter IV Kidney Dialysis, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3969)
  - History Project Photo Ideas: Chapter V Artificial Heart, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3970)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter VI Cardiac Care, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3971)
  - History Project Photo Ideas: Chapter VII Babies, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3972)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter VIII Hyperbaric Chamber, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3973)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter X Light and Heat, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3974)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter XI Eyes, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3975)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter XII Ears, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3976)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter XIII Burns and Microsurgery, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3977)
  - History Project Photos: Chapter XIV Transplant, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3978)
  - History Project Photo Ideas: Chapter XV Cancer, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3979)
  - History Project Photos: General, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3980)
  - History Project: Photo Houses, 1983 (Box 532, Folder 3981)
  - History Project: Photo Lists, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3982)
  - History Project Photos: Hartford Family, 1980 (Box 532, Folder 3983)
  - History Project: Photographs for Book, 1983 (Box 532, Folder 3984)
  - Board Book Materials, 1987-1988 (Box 533, Folder 3985-3986)
  - Budget, 1987-1988 (Box 533, Folder 3987-3988)
  - Quarterly Financial Highlights, 1986-1987 (Box 533, Folder 3989)
  - Corinne Rieder Files: Strategic Plan Board Presentations, 1998-2008 (Box 533, Folder 3990-3995)
  - Corinne Rieder Files: Jonas Center for Nursing Excellence promotional video, Interview with Corinne Rieder of John A. Hartford Foundation, 2006; 1 DVD (Box 2015:065:006, Folder 3994)
  - Lease Correspondence for Office in Chrysler Building (405 Lexington Avenue), 1979-1986 (Box 534, Folder 3996-3998)
  - Office in Chrysler Building (405 Lexington Avenue), 1979 (Box 534, Folder 3999)
  - Blueprints for Former JAHF Office in Chrysler Building (405 Lexington Avenue), 1979; Oversized blueprints and whiteprints (Box 2014:023:026, Folder 3999)
  - John A. Hartford Foundation Sale of A&P Stock, 1976 (Box 534, Folder 4000-4002)
  - Acrylic Paperweight of A&P Common Stock Sale Prospectus, 1976; Acrylic paperweight (Box 2014:023:027, Folder 4001)
  - Clippings on A&P, 1947-1973 (Box 534, Folder 4003)
  - Univesity of Guam (84-147, declined): S. Winter, 1984 (Box 534, Folder 4004)
  - University of Tennessee: Award for John A. Hartford Foundation, 1982 (Box 534, Folder 4005)
  - University of Tennessee: Wooden Award to John A. Hartford Foundation, 1982; Wooden award (Box 2014:023:028, Folder 4005)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Financial Journal, 1951-1954 (Box 535, Folder 4006)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Settlement Report, 1954 (Box 535, Folder 4007)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cemetery Trust Correspondence, 1954-1984 (Box 535, Folder 4008)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cemetery Trust Accounting, 1950-1981 (Box 535, Folder 4009)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cemetery Trust Balance Sheets, 1969-1983 (Box 535, Folder 4010)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cemetery Trust: Corwin Plot. John Augustus Hartford on Horseback., 1948; 1 black-and-white photograph (Box 535, Folder 4011)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cemetery Trust: Corwin Plot Plans, Hillside Cemetery, Middletown, New York, 1948; 2 oversized whiteprint plans (Box 2014:023:029, Folder 4011)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Cash Receipts, 1950-1955 (Box 536, Folder 4012)
  - Estate of John A. Hartford: Fortune Magazine Article on Hartford Family and A&P, 1933 March (Box 536, Folder 4013)